Guide to the Anthony Imbert Lithographs 1825–circa 1835, undated PR 225
New-York Historical Society
Anthony Imbert lithographs
1825–circa 1835, undated
New-York Historical Society
Imbert, Anthony, 1794 or 1795-1834
PR 225
1.24 Linear feet in 1 box and 1 drawer.
Thirty-five prints by the French-American lithographer Anthony Imbert after drawings by the artists Alexander Jackson Davis, Dominico Canova, Gherlando Marsiglia, and Antonio Meucci. Along with views of locations in Brooklyn, the Bronx, and upstate New York, the collection includes a number of Manhattan scenes produced as plates for Cadwallader Colden's Memoir prepared at the request of the Common Council of New York, and presented to the mayor of the city, at the celebration of the completion of the New York Canals (New York: W. A. Davis, 1825), and for Davis's Views of The Public Buildings in the City of New-York [1826–1828]. Also present are several portraits, and one of the earliest pieces of sheet music lithographed in New York.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in nine categories:
Plates from Cadwallader Colden, Memoir prepared at the request of the Common Council of New York, and presented to the mayor of the city, at the celebration of the completion of the New York Canals, 1825
Plates from Views of The Public Buildings in the City of New-York, [1826–1828]
Other views of Manhattan, undated
Views of Brooklyn, undated
Views of The Bronx, undated
Views of New York State, 1829, circa 1835, undated
Portraits, [1830–1831], undated
Sheet music, [1823–1826]
Miscellaneous, circa 1826, 1829–1835, undated
Biographical / Historical
Lithographer Anthony Imbert (1794 or 1795–1834) was born in France and came to the United States in 1824 or 1825. Imbert immediately opened a lithographic firm, and very quickly became the premier lithographer in New York City. He printed images by artists such as Alexander Jackson Davis, Dominico Canova, Gherlando Marsiglia, and Antonio Meucci. Under the name "Imbert's Lithography," Imbert produced lithographed views of buildings in New York City, several views of Niagara Falls and New York State, portraits of eminent men, drawing books, and cartoons and caricatures.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection is comprised of gifts from multiple donors.
Related Materials
For the title page and other lithographs and architectural drawings from Views of The Public Buildings in the City of New-York [1826–1828], see the Alexander Jackson Davis Architectural Drawing Collection (PR-016). The New-York Historical Society's library holds multiple, complete copies of Cadwallader Colden's Memoir prepared at the request of the Common Council of New York, and presented to the mayor of the city, at the celebration of the completion of the New York Canals (New York: W. A. Davis, 1825).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains plates from Cadwallader Colden's Memoir prepared at the request of the Common Council of New York, and presented to the mayor of the city, at the celebration of the completion of the New York Canals (New York: W. A. Davis, 1825), a book which was published to celebrate the opening of the Erie Canal and was the first monumental book with lithographic plates. Several of these plates are views of local fire companies. Also included are many views of New York City buildings; some drawn by A. J. Davis in 1827–1828 and published as Views of The Public Buildings in the City of New-York [1826–1828]. A broadside with an illustration of the American Hotel is also included. Views of buildings in Brooklyn and the Bronx are included, as are two lithographs of Niagara Falls. A piece of sheet music, one of the earliest to be lithographed in New York, is also part of the collection.
Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; Erie Canal (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.) -- Pictorial works.; Lithography -- Printing -- Specimens.; Lithographs.; Sheet music.; Canova, Dominico, 1800-1868; Davis, Alexander Jackson, 1803-1892; Marsiglia, Gherlando, 1792-1850; Meucci, Antonio, 1808-1889; Imbert's Lithographic Office; New York (N.Y.). Fire Department -- Pictorial works
- 1. Plates from Cadwallader Colden, Memoir prepared at the request of the Common Council of New York, and presented to the mayor of the city, at the celebration of the completion of the New York Canals (New York: W. A. Davis), 1825
  - Plate 08: "Deep Cutting. Lockport," drawn by George Catlin, [1825] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Plate 20: "Fire Department" [Washington #20], drawn by Dominico Canova, [1825] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Plate 21: "Fire Department" [East River Co. 42], drawn by W. H. Tuthill, [1825] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Plate 22: "Fire Department" [Fire Dept #15], drawn by W. P. Morgan, [1825] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Plate 27: "Grand Canal Celebration. No XXII. Hook and Ladder Company," drawn by Dominico Canova, [1825] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- 2. Plates from Views of The Public Buildings in the City of New-York, [1826–1828]
  - "New York Theatre," drawn by A. J. Davis, [1826–1828] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Castle Garden, N. York," drawn by A. J. Davis (hand colored), [1826–1828] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Phenix Bank," drawn by A. J. Davis, [1826–1828] (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-1)
  - "Merchants Exchange," drawn by A. J. Davis (2 copies), [1826–1828] (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-1)
  - "Masonic Hall" [Broadway, 314–316], drawn by A. J. Davis, [1826–1828] (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-1)
  - "Second Congregational Church, N. Y.," drawn by A. J. Davis, [1826–1828] (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-2)
  - "Branch Bank of U. S." [Wall Street, 30–32], drawn by A. J. Davis, [1826–1828] (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-2)
  - "St. Thomas Church, Broadway," drawn by A. J. Davis, [1826–1828] (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-3)
  - "Lafayette Theater," drawn by A. J. Davis, [1826–1828] (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-3)
- 3. Other views of Manhattan, undated
  - "American Hotel," [Broadway, 229], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - "United States Hotel" [Pearl Street, 178–180], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - [City Hall Park, design for improving the old Alms House Park], drawn by J. M. Roberts, undated (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-4)
- 4. Views of Brooklyn, undated
  - "View of Erasmus Hall Academy Flatbush L.I.", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Brooklyn Collegiate Institute for Young Ladies. Opposite N. York," drawn by J. M. Roberts (2 copies; 1 hand colored), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- 5. Views of The Bronx, undated
  - "The Doric Mansion, on Throgs Neck," drawn by A. J. Davis (2 copies), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- 6. Views of New York State, 1829, circa 1835, undated
  - "Catskill Falls," drawn after his own design by Gherlando Marsiglia, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Entrance to the Highlands," lithographed for the Rural Repository, 1829 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Niagara Falls. Part of the American Fall from the foot of the staircase," drawn by Gherlando Marsiglia after the Bennett-Hill aquatint (hand colored), circa 1835 (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-5)
  - "Niagara Falls. Part of the British Fall, taken from under the Table Rock," drawn by Gherlando Marsiglia after the Bennett-Hill aquatint, circa 1835 (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-5)
- 7. Portraits, [1830–1831], undated
  - "John Augustine Smith," drawn by Dominico Canova, [1830–1831] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Blind mat man of New York," drawn by Antonio Meucci, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - [Mr. John Roulstone at the New York Riding School], undated (Drawer 1, Folder Oversize-6)
- 8. Sheet music, [1823–1826]
  - "Constantinople; Musique Turque for the Pianoforte," sheet music with image drawn by Dominico Canova, [1823–1826] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- 9. Miscellaneous, circa 1826, 1829–1835, undated
  - "Magnanimity of the Elephant, Displayed in the Preservation of his Keeper in the Bowery Menageries in New York in Dec. 1826," drawn by A. Meucci after his own design, [circa 1826] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Monument to John Paulding," on verso of above, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Untitled. A man on a country lane with "Half Way" signpost] drawn by E. Rousseau, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Four vignettes], circa 1829–1835 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)